Guide to the Gordon Moore Papers M1965
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Gordon Moore papers
1958-2005
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Moore, Gordon E., 1929-
Gordon and Betty Moore Foundation
M1965
53.6 Linear Feet 97 boxes (79 manuscript boxes, 18 flat boxes)
180 gigabyte(s)
The papers of Gordon E. Moore, co-founder of the Intel Corporation and author of "Moore's Law", document his professional and personal life, covering his roles at Intel and his many activities outside of the Intel Corporation, how he invested his time and money, and his engagement with many organizations and individuals in business, politics, science, academia, philanthropy, and conservation.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of business correspondence related to Intel Corporation, reports, overhead transparencies, presentation slides related to Intel Corporation and the semiconductor industry. Also included are photographs, slides, calendars, audiocassettes, videocassettes, and publications relating to Moore’s career as President and Chairman of Intel Corporation as well as his work in other organizations. The collection spans from 1958-2005, but the bulk of the material falls within the years 1968-1996.
Intel reviewed the collection and flagged a large portion as secret or restricted because they may contain proprietary or other sensitive information. The items flagged by Intel have been separated from the collection and will be returned to Intel. While the folders retain their original titles prior to the materials being separated the titles but may no longer reflect the folder's contents.
Biographical / Historical
Gordon Earle Moore (1929- ), co-founder of Intel Corporation and progenitor of “Moore’s Law,” was born in San Francisco. He grew up in in the small town of Pescadero where his father, Walter Harold Moore, was the San Mateo County Deputy Sheriff and his mother, born Florence Almira "Mira" Williamson, was a homemaker. The Moores had been in Pescadero since the 1840s. Moore’s father became the Chief Deputy Sheriff and the family moved to Redwood City where Moore grew interested in chemistry and graduated from Sequoia High School. He met his future wife Betty Whitaker while attending San Jose State College, then transferred to the University of California, Berkeley and received a chemistry degree in 1950. Moore then went to the California Institute of Technology and was awarded a PhD in chemistry and physics in 1954. After graduation Gordon and Betty moved to Maryland where he worked as a researcher at the Applied Physics Laboratory run by John Hopkins University.
Two years later Moore joined William Shockley, Nobel Prize winner and co-inventor of the transistor, at the Shockley Semiconductor Laboratory in Palo Alto, California. However, Moore was among the “Traitorous Eight” who left Shockley to start the Fairchild Semiconductor Corporation in 1957 where he served as Director of Research and Development. Moore and Robert Noyce left Fairchild in July 1968 to establish the Intel Corporation in Santa Clara with the initial goal of developing and producing large scale integrated products. They were soon joined by another scientist from Fairchild, Andrew Grove. Moore initially served as Executive Vice President and in 1975 he became President and Chief Executive Officer. In April 1979 Moore was elected Chairman of the Board and Chief Executive Officer. In April 1987 he became Chairman of the Board, which he held for next 10 years. Moore was Chairman Emeritus of Intel Corporation from 1997 until stepping down in 2006.
Moore is well known for “Moore’s Law,” which states that the number of electrical components on a computer chip would double each year. In 1975 he updated the prediction to once every two years. This principle enabled the semiconductor industry to decrease the cost of electronics while creating more powerful chips. In addition, Dr. Moore is a director of Transamerica Corporation, Gilead Sciences and Varian Associates and was Chairman of the Board of Trustees of Caltech from 1995 to 2001. He and his wife Betty founded the Gordon and Betty Moore Foundation in 2000. The foundation is one of the biggest foundations and focuses on environmental conservation, patient care, science, and projects in the San Francisco Bay Area.
Dr. Moore has received multiple awards over the years including the Distinguished Alumnus Award from Caltech, W.W. McDowell Award from the IEEE Computer Society, Frederik Philips Award, Harry Goode Award for Leadership in Science, Computer Pioneer Medal of IEEE, Founders Award, National Medal of Technology and the John Fritz Medal.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into five series:
1. Notebooks, 1968-1995 2. Chronological Files, 1958-2003 I. Correspondence, Minutes and Other Material affiliated with Gordon Moore, 1958-2002 II. Outgoing Business Correspondence from Gordon Moore, 1984-2003 III. Intel Corporation Financial Reports, 1969-1995 IV. Calendars, 1974-1999 3. Alphabetical Files, 1968-1999 4. Photographs and Slides, 1964-1998 5. Audiovisual Materials, 1975-2005
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open for research, with the exception of one box. Series 2: Chronological Files contains one box closed until the year 2023. Note that material must be requested at least 36 hours in advance of intended use.
Selected audiovisual and other material from this collection has been digitized and is available e in the Special Collections reading room or via Searchworks for Stanford-affiliated patrons: https://searchworks.stanford.edu/view/10626780
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Gordon Moore, 2013. Accession 2013-107 and 2013-115
Businesspeople; Charge coupled devices; Chemists; Computer engineering; Computer engineers; Computer science -- Very large scale integration; Electronic industries.; Entrepreneurship; Integrated Circuits; Metal oxide semiconductors -- History; Microcomputers; Microelectronics industry -- California -- Santa Clara County; Microprocessors; Moore's law; Random access memory; Semiconductor industry.; Semiconductors; Moore, Gordon E., 1929-; Noyce, Robert N. (Robert Norton), 1927-1990; Grove, Andrew S.; Advanced Micro Devices (Firm); American Electronics Association; AT & T (Firm); California Institute of Technology; Conservation International; Dataquest (Firm); Fairchild (Firm); Ford Motor Company; Gilead Sciences (Firm); Horatio Alger Association of Distinguished Americans; Institute of Electrical and Electronics Engineers; Intel Corporation; International Business Machines Corporation.; Joint Venture: Silicon Valley Network (Organization); Microsoft Corporation; National Academies (U.S.); National Academy of Engineering; NEC Electronics; San José State University; Sandia National Laboratories; SEMATECH (Organization); Semiconductor Equipment and Materials Institute; Semiconductor Industry Association; Semiconductor Research Corporation; Texas Instruments Incorporated.; Transamerica Corporation; United Way of America; Varian Associates; Gordon and Betty Moore Foundation
- Series 1: Notebooks, 1968-1988; 1 Linear Feet
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains material from Gordon Moore’s main office cubicle at Intel. The notebooks in this series cover topics such as litigation strategy, IBM, technology, SEMATECH, management, Texas Instruments, patents, Project Pluto and Project Orion.
  - Patent notebook, 8 x 10, hardcover, “Intel #1,” entries [Originally in Box 1, Folder 1], 8 October 1968 - 5 May 1970 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Hardcover notebook, 8 x 10, GEM notes of internal and customer meetings and calls [Originally in Box 1, Folder 2], October 1973-September 1982 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Composition book, hardcover, 7.5 x 9.5, “ ‘A JOBS’ IE THINGS I REALLY SHOULD DO.” To-do lists and aide memoir notes [Originally in Box 1, Folder 3], 1972 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Composition book, hardcover, 7.5 x 9.5, “Misc. Tech. Meetings,” Notes from internal technical meetings. Notes include meetings on Intel Shottky bipolar process, Dov Frohman’s FAMOS (EPROM), early device packaging, and other topics [Originally in Box 1, Folder 4], September 1969-September 1970 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Composition book, hardcover, 7.75 x 10, “G. Moore,” Notes on internal and external business and technology meetings, starting on date of incorporation 15 July 1968 to the announcement of the first product around 13 June 1969 [Originally in Box 1, Folder 5], 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Composition book, hardcover, 7.5 x 9.5, “State of the nation, technically. GE Moore.” Notes and summaries of technical, device, and packaging issues and meetings [Originally in Box 1, Folder 7], June 1969-September 1970 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Composition book, hardcover, 7.5 x 9.5, “Misc. Planning & Decision Meetings. GE Moore.” Notes on internal technical and product decision-making meetings and planning meetings [Originally in Box 1, Folder 8], June 1969-August 1969 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Composition book, hardcover, 7.5 x 9.5, “MONDAY MTNGS.” Notes on two weekly meetings, [Originally in Box 1, Folder 9], February 1970-July 1970 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Composition book, hardcover, 7.5 x 9.5, “Tech Mtngs,” Notes of internal technical discussions on issues relating to microprocessors, process technology, and ion implantation [Originally in Box 1, Folder 10], February 1972-April 1972 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Writing Pads 8.5 x 11.5, from hanging folder labeled “ASG-RNN MTNGS.” Tablets contain Moore’s notes from meetings with Andrew Grove and Robert Noyce, [Originally in Box 2, Folder 1], December 1976-March 1980 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Writing Pads, 8.5 x 11.5, from hanging folder labeled “ASG-RNN MTNGS.” Tablets contain Moore’s notes from meetings with Andrew Grove and Robert Noyce [Originally in Box 2, Folder 2], July 1980-February 1985 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Photocopied documents from folder labeled “Intel, 1968-9”; Staffing, Equipment, Bipolar device products c. 1969, 1968 product schedules, 1969; Marketing report, January 1969; operations progress report, MOS process development in 1969, March 1969 operations progress report, Pasadena operations and founding agreement [Originally in Box 2, Folder 9], August 1968-March 1969 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Photocopied documents from folder labeled “SEMATECH.” Documents concerning the establishment and early activities of SEMATECH and Intel’s strategies for its participation (1 of 2) [Originally in Box 2, Folder 11], 1987-1988 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Photocopied documents from folder labeled “MISC MANAGEMENT MATERIAL,” Several documents from Moore’s attendance at management seminars and meetings with management consultants [Originally in Box 3, Folder 1], 1972-1986 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Photocopied documents from folder labeled “TOTAL QUALITY.” Two documents: an article on IBM quality practices and an Intel internal planning document on management and strategy changes [Originally in Box 3, Folder 3], 1986 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Series 2: Chronological Files, 1958-2003
  This series is the largest in the collection. The series is composed of notes, charts, graphs, slides, and overhead transparencies for lectures, conferences, and meetings with various semiconductor related associations, universities, and other organizations; materials related to Intel corporation, including notes, correspondence, charts, reports, and agendas; outgoing correspondence from Gordon Moore; annual and quarterly reports and financial data; and calendars used by Gordon Moore. There is also a small amount of news clippings and publications.
  Note: Items flagged by Intel have been separated and will be returned to Intel.
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged in 4 sub-series. Sub-Series I: Correspondence, Minutes and Other Material affiliated with Gordon Moore, 1958-2002; Sub-Series II: Outgoing Business Correspondence from Gordon Moore, 1984-2003; Sub-Series III: Intel Corporation Financial Reports, 1969-1995; Sub-Series IV: Calendars, 1974-1999.
  - Sub-Series I: Correspondence, Minutes and Other Material affiliated with Gordon Moore, 1958-2003
    This series is the largest in the collection. The files have been kept in their original chronological order. The series is comprised of board meeting agendas, minutes, reports, and notes related to Intel Corporation. There are also presentation slides and overhead transparencies for lectures, conferences, and meetings with various semiconductor related associations, universities and other related companies as well as other materials for conferences and meetings. It also consists of correspondence with Intel staff (i.e. Andrew Grove, Robert Noyce).
    - Intel Corp. Gordon E. Moore Biographical Article [Originally in Box 5, Folder 1], undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Fairchild Semiconductor Corp. - “Customized Large-Scale Integration” article by Gordon E. Moore [Originally in Box 5, Folder 2], undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Fairchild Semiconductor Corp. - Progress Reports [Originally in Box 5, Folder 3], 1958 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Fairchild Semiconductor Corp. - Miscellaneous Correspondence [Originally in Box 5, Folder 4], 1958-1960 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - “Junction Transistors” Article by Gordon E. Moore, Correspondence [Originally in Box 5, Folder 6], 1960-1961 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - “The Strengths, Widths, and Shapes of Lines in the Vibration-Rotation Bands of CO” by Robert Herman, William S. Benedict, Gordon Moore and Shirleigh Silverman, The Astrophysical Journal, Vol. 135, No. 1 [Originally in Box 5, Folder 6], January 1962 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Molecular Electronics Article, Correspondence, Drawings [Originally in Box 5, Folder 7], 1962 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - “The MOS (Metal-Oxide-Semiconductor) Transistor as an Individual Device and in Integrated Arrays” Article [Originally in Box 5, Folder 8], 1965 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - “Metal-Oxide-Semiconductor Field-Effect Devices for Micropower Logic Circuitry” by Gordon E. Moore, C.T. Sah, F.M. Wanlass [Originally in Box 5, Folder 9], April 1963 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Fairchild Semiconductor Corp. - News clippings, re: Robert Noyce, Integrated Circuits [Originally in Box 5, Folder 11], 1964 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Integrated Electronics Articles, Correspondence, Graphs, re: “The Future of Integrated Electronics,” “Integrated Electronics Circa 1980” [Originally in Box 5, Folder 13], 1965-1966 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Photocopies of Integrated Electronics Articles [Originally in Box 6, Folder 1], 1965 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Moore’s Law articles, magazine, re: “Cramming more components onto integrated circuits,” “The Future of Integrated Circuits,” Presentation Slides [Originally in Box 6, Folder 2], 1965 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - “The MOS (Metal-Oxide-Semiconductor) Transistor as an Individual Device and in Integrated Arrays” Article, Correspondence for IEEE [Originally in Box 6, Folder 3], 1965 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Semiconductor Tetrode Patent, Fairchild Semiconductor Corp. Correspondence [Originally in Box 6, Folder 4], September 1966 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Fall Joint Computer Conference (FJCC) Presentation by Gordon E. Moore, re: Large Scale Integration [Originally in Box 6, Folder 5], 1967 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Large Scale Integrated Electronics Research Papers for IEEE International Convention, “On Feasibility of Large Scale Integration,” Correspondence, re: Customized Large Scale Integration, Future of Integrated Electronics [Originally in Box 6, Folder 6], 1967-1968 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - “Semiconductor Memories” Research Paper, Correspondence, Presentation Notes after Intermag Conference [Originally in Box 6, Folder 8], April 1968 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - IEEE Electron Devices Meeting re: “Trends in Silicon Device Technology” Research Paper, Slide List, Notes, Graphs, Correspondence [Originally in Box 6, Folder 9], 1968-1969 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Intel Corp. Schematics - Diagrams re: 2001, Charts, Double Masking Process Flow, Silicon Processing, Graphs, Overhead Transparencies [Originally in Box 7, Folder 2], 1968-1972 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - “Semiconductor Memories - Device Aspects” Research Paper, Graphs, Program, Presentation Notes re: IEEE International Convention [Originally in Box 8, Folder 1], March 1969 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Intel Corp. Annual Stockholders Meeting - Minutes, Correspondence, Notes, Articles [Originally in Box 8, Folder 2], April-May 1969 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Intel Corp. Article, re: “What Level of LSI (Large Scale Integration) is Best for You?” [Originally in Box 8, Folder 3], February 1970 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Intel Corp. Correspondence, Research Papers, Notes, Diagrams, re: “Looking into Silicon Crystal Ball to Project Circuit Costs” published in Electronics Magazine [Originally in Box 8, Folder 4], 1970 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Philco Management Group - Presentation Notes [Originally in Box 8, Folder 5], February 1970 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - IEEE Panel “New Directions for Memories” - Research Papers, Correspondence, Graphs, Notes, re: “Competitive Potential of Semiconductor Materials" [Originally in Box 8, Folder 6], 1970 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - IEEE International Conference on Ion Implantation in Semiconductors - Correspondence, Notes, Map [Originally in Box 8, Folder 7], May 1970 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - IEEE Computer Group Annual Conference - Correspondence, Brochures, Notes, Research Paper re: “In Defense of Single Technology Approach to Semiconductor Main Frame Memories for the 70’s” [Originally in Box 8, Folder 8], June 1970 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Monsanto Management Meeting - Presentation Notes [Originally in Box 8, Folder 9], June 1970 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Solid State Circuits Council - Correspondence, Mailing List [Originally in Box 9, Folder 1], 1970-1971 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - University of Washington Device Research Conference - Correspondence [Originally in Box 9, Folder 2], July 1970 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Wescon Symposium - Program, Correspondence, re: Applying High Technology to Public Problems [Originally in Box 9, Folder 3], August 1970 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Fourth Annual Solid State Devices Conference, University of Exeter - Correspondence, Programs, Research Paper, Notes re: Semiconductor Storage, Diagrams [Originally in Box 9, Folder 5], September 1970 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Intel Corp. Correspondence, Notes, Diagrams re: Addo Calculators [Originally in Box 9, Folder 6], September 1970 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Intermag (International Magnetics) Conference - Diagrams, Program, Correspondence, Notes re: A Perspective of Charge Transfer Devices and Other Shift Registers [Originally in Box 9, Folder 8], April 1971 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Large Scale Integration Symposium - Program, Notes, Research Paper re: Memory Components and Technology [Originally in Box 9, Folder 9], June 1971 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Intel Corp. Sales Newsletter re: Large-Scale Integrated Electronics [Originally in Box 9, Folder 10], July 1971 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Buhl International Conference on Materials - Correspondence, Diagrams, Research Paper re: Large Scale Integrated Electronics [Originally in Box 10, Folder 1], November 1971 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - SSDRC (Solid State Device Research Conference), Edmonton, Canada - Notes, Session Agendas, Computer Magazine, March/April 1971 issue [Originally in Box 10, Folder 4], June 1972 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Caltech Notes, Overhead Transparencies, re: Integrated Electronics [Originally in Box 10, Folder 5], November 1972 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - IEEE International Convention - Presentation Notes [Originally in Box 10, Folder 6], March 1972 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - IEEE International Convention - Correspondence, Technical Papers, re: Semiconductor Main Frame Memories [Originally in Box 10, Folder 7], 1973 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Intel Corp. Graphs and Presentation Slides re: Sabe Conference, San Francisco [Originally in Box 10, Folder 8], 1973 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Bell Laboratories Metal-Oxide-Silicon Field Effect Transistor (MOSFET) Award Correspondence, Copies of Patents 1933-1966 [Originally in Box 10, Folder 9], 1973-1974 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - Caltech Fundraiser Campaign - Correspondence, Handbooks, Pamphlet, Engineering and Science Journal, February 1974 issue [Originally in Box 10, Folder 11] (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - American Institute of Mining, Metallurgical and Petroleum Engineers, Inc. Second Annual Electronic Materials Symposium - Program, Speaker Notes re: Integrated Electric Technology, Graphs, Presentation Slides [Originally in Box 11, Folder 1], March 1974 (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - Microelectronics Journal Correspondence re: Honorary Editorial Advisory Board [Originally in Box 11, Folder 3], 1974, 1978 (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - Caltech/Jet Propulsion Laboratory - Graphs, Correspondence, Notes, Presentation Slides re: Integrated Electronics Costs [Originally in Box 11, Folder 4], March 1975 (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - Caltech/Jet Propulsion Laboratory - Correspondence, Presentation Slides from Conference re: Large Scale Integration and Microprocessor Revolution, Caltech Regional Advisory Council Directory [Originally in Box 11, Folder 5], 1975 (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - INTERFACE ‘75/Kodak Microelectronics Seminar - Diagrams, Correspondence, Notes, Article re: “Progress in Digital Integrated Electronics” [Originally in Box 11, Folder 7], 1975, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - IEEE Proceedings, Vol. 64, No. 6, June 1976 - Article re: Microprocessors and Integrated Electronic Technology, Correspondence, Research Paper by Richard L. Petritz re: Emerging Role and Impact of the Microprocessor [Originally in Box 11, Folder 9] (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - MSD (Mass Storage Device) Sales Conference - Speaker Notes, Overhead Transparencies, Presentation Slides [Originally in Box 11, Folder 10], March 1976 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Electro76 Convention (International Convention of the Institute of Electrical and Electronics Engineers) - Programs, Correspondence, Research Paper, Graphs re: “Progress in Digital Integrated Electronics” [Originally in Box 12, Folder 1], 1975-1976 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Sandia Laboratories, University of California, Berkeley - Presentation re: Integrated Electronics Technology, Overhead Transparencies, Notes, Correspondence, Research Papers [Originally in Box 12, Folder 3], October 1976 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Intel Corp. Plan 77.0 - Correspondence, Notes, Presentation Slides, Program Guidelines, Graphs [Originally in Box 12, Folder 4], November 1976 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - EEE Chicago Fall Conference on Consumer Electronics Awards Luncheon -Correspondence, Graphs, Programs, Presentation Slides, Notes, Newsletter re: “Cost Structure of Semiconductor Industry and Its Implications for Consumer Electronics” [Originally in Box 12, Folder 5], December 1976 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - New York Society of Security Analysts Semiconductor Memories Seminar - Correspondence, Notes [Originally in Box 12, Folder 7], 1976-1977 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Intel Corp. Microcomputer Division Product - Presentation Slides re: Microcomputer Components [Originally in Box 12, Folder 8], March 1977 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Intel Corp. Shareholders Meeting - Notes, Presentation Slides, Charts [Originally in Box 12, Folder 9], 1976-1977 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - IEEE Santa Clara Valley Electron Devices Panel Presentation - Notes, Correspondence, San Francisco Bay Area Council Newsletter [Originally in Box 12, Folder 10], April 1977 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Advanced Electronics Symposium, Litton Industries Presentation - Notes, Agenda, Correspondence, Diagrams, Presentation Slides, Pocket Directory [Originally in Box 12, Folder 11], 1977 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Fourteenth Symposium on Electron, Ion and Photon Beam Technology Presentation - Notes, Program, Correspondence [Originally in Box 12, Folder 12], May 1977 (Box 6, Folder 11)